{"tossups": [{"question": "This man wrote a book predicting the downfall of religion entitled <em>The Future of an Illusion</em> and advanced the theory that Egyptian Aten-worship directly inspired Judaism in <em>Moses and</em> <em>Monotheism</em>. This man used patients such as Little Hans and Irma to develop his theory of the latent subconscious in a book which \"began the twentieth century,\" <em>The Interpretation of</em> <em>Dreams.</em> For, the point, name this Austrian father of psychoanalysis.", "answer": "Sigmund <b><u>Freud</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "Admiral John Crace from this nation led a task force that foiled Operation MO as part of the first naval battle in history in which opposing ships never saw each other. Along with the USA, this country provided most of the allied troops in the New Guinea campaign. For the point, name this nation, an invasion of which was foiled by a victory at the Battle of the Coral Sea, but which suffered the bombing of Darwin from Japanese forces.", "answer": "<b><u>Australia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This material first became available in toothbrushes in 1939, after its invention the prior year by Wallace Carothers at DuPont. This material, which is a trade name for aliphatic polyamides, was used to replace silk in parachutes during World War II; it is now used in Glock handguns and has became synonymous with women's stockings. For the point, name this early synthetic polymer.", "answer": "<b><u>nylon</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "This man played Republican Presidential candidate Jasper Irving in the Afghan war drama <em>Lions for Lambs</em>. In other historical roles, he portrayed Ron Kovic in Oliver Stone's Vietnam veterans film <em>Born on the Fourth of July</em>; Nathan Algren, the protagonist of <em>The Last Samurai</em>; and anti-Hitler plotter Claus von Stauffenberg in <em>Valkyrie</em>. For the point, name this movie star known for his recurring role in the <em>Mission Impossible</em> series and his Scientology beliefs.", "answer": "Tom <b><u>Cruise</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The remains of one of these objects at Belitung included many Tang dynasty artifacts. Before petroleum power was developed, a main use of pitch was to coat these objects in a procedure known as caulking. The lateen rig appears on an Arab type of these called the <em>dhow</em>, which was often sent between Yemen and Mogadishu. For the point, name these vehicles whose early types include the East Asian junk.", "answer": "<b><u>boat</u></b>s [or <b><u>ship</u></b>s]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A member of this family took on the name \"Tania\" to rob the Hibernia Bank, after which she pled Stockholm Syndrome to avoid being implicated in the Symbionese Liberation Army's activities. An earlier member of this family built a \"castle\" in San Simeon and ran the <em>New York</em> <em>Journal</em> as the bitter rival of Joseph Pulitzer. For the point, name this family of media moguls that was founded by the inspiration for <em>Citizen Kane</em>, William Randolph.", "answer": "<b><u>Hearst</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state's lieutenant governor Mead Treadwell declined to run for re-election in 2014 due to a Senate bid. Democratic nominee Byron Mallott ended his campaign to become the running mate of the independent candidate for governor in this state, who defeated incumbent Republican Sean Parnell. For the point, name this state which elected Bill Walker as its new governor, ending his time as mayor of Valdez and filling an office once held by Sarah Palin.", "answer": "<b><u>Alaska</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Constantine I introduced a type of these items called the <em>solidus</em> to replace the earlier <em>aureus</em>. Dead people were buried with one of these objects called an <em>obol</em> in their mouths. Roman types of these things include the <em>sestertius</em> & the <em>denarius</em>, while Greeks used the <em>drachma</em>. For the point, name these objects, made from silver or gold, that were exchanged for goods & services.", "answer": "<b><u>coin</u></b>s [or <b><u>money</u></b>; or <b><u>currency</u></b>; or other equivalents]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This city's history is related in the Laurentian Codex, which contains Nestor's <em>Primary</em> <em>Chronicle</em>. Boleslaw Chobry struck this city\u2019s Golden Gate with his sword. Hilarion was made Metropolitan of this city by its Grand Prince Yaroslav the Wise. This city was converted to Christianity by Vladimir I. In 1941, this city's Jews were massacred in the Babi Yar ravine. For the point, name this first capital of the Rus and the current capital of Ukraine.", "answer": "<b><u>Kiev</u></b> [or <b><u>Kyiv</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first major politician to push this idea was Lewis Cass, during the 1848 Democratic Presidential campaign. This idea was the subject of the Freeport Doctrine, and it was codified in the Kansas-Nebraska Act, both of which were the work of its most vocal proponent, Stephen Douglas. For the point, identify this antebellum idea which said that American territories should decide on whether to allow slavery through a vote.", "answer": "<b><u>popular sovereignty</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This author used Nikolay Karamzin\u2019s <em>History of the Russian State</em> as the source for a play which the monk Grigory Otrepyev (<b>OH-trep-yev</b>) pretends to be the assassinated Dmitri. The 1824 flood of the Neva (<b>NEE-vah</b>) River provided the background for his story in which an equestrian monument of Peter the Great comes to life. For the point, name this author of <em>Boris</em> <em>Gudonov</em> and <em>The Bronze Horseman</em>, the \"father of Russian literature.\"", "answer": "Alexander <b><u>Pushkin</u></b> [Alexander Sergeyevich <b><u>Pushkin</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "During this man's administration, the Ashley's Hundred company began their fur-trading expedition, and the Denmark Vesey slave rebellion occurred. This President oversaw the resolution of the Arbuthnot and Ambrister incident during the First Seminole War. This man's Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams, acquired Florida for the U.S. and wrote his \"doctrine.\" For the point, name this President during the Era of Good Feelings.", "answer": "James <b><u>Monroe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This practice was endorsed by the first article of the Schletheim Confession. A follower of Zwingli named Conrad Grebel became one of the first to engage in this practice near Zurich in 1525. The theological justification for this practice was that only people who could recognize and repent of their sins could have them washed away. For the point, name this central practice of the Anabaptists which held that infants could not receive a certain sacrament.", "answer": "<b><u>adult baptism</u></b> [or <b><u>rebaptism</u></b>] (prompt on just <b><u>baptism</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "One of this nation\u2019s former colonies was then controlled for several decades by Indonesia; that was East Timor. This nation also lost one territory in 1961\u2019s Operation Vijay, in which India annexed Goa. For the point, name this European colonial power which controlled Mozambique and Angola, and which saw the overthrow of Antonio Salazar\u2019s Estado Novo in the Carnation Revolution in Lisbon.", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Charles Cooper invented the lanthanum fluoride process as part of this program, which was infiltrated by Morris Cohen. A letter drafted by Leo Szilard (<b>ZIL-ard</b>) helped kickstart this program, which was also the target of spying by David Greenglass, and was supervised by Leslie Groves. Enrico Fermi and Albert Einstein also persuaded Franklin Roosevelt to authorize this project. For the point, name this effort which oversaw the Trinity test of the first atomic bomb.", "answer": "<b><u>Manhattan</u></b> Project", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In an etching, this artist depicted himself asleep while bats and owls harass him. This artist included <em>The Sleep of Reason Produces Monsters</em> in his <em>Los Caprichos</em> series, and he depicted a <em>Charge of the Mamelukes</em> in a different series. In a painting by this artist, a Christ-like figure in white stretches out his arms before soldiers of Napoleon execute him and his comrades. For the point, name this painter of the <em>Disasters of War</em> series, which includes <em>The Third of May, 1808</em>.", "answer": "Francisco <b><u>Goya</u></b> [Francisco Jose de <b><u>Goya</u></b> y Lucientes]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man was replaced by Matthew Ridgway in his highest post. He said that people of his profession \"just fade away\" in a speech about how \"old soldiers never die.\" This corncob-pipe enthusiast proclaimed \"I shall return\" when he left the Philippines in World War II, and he had earlier been sent by President Hoover to disperse the Bonus Army. For the point, name this general whose clashes with Harry Truman caused him to be removed from command in Korea.", "answer": "Douglas <b><u>MacArthur</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This language provided the base for the creoles Pejto (<b>PET-yo</b>) and Javindo (<b>yah-VIN-doh</b>). This language never achieved more than two percent adoption in Indonesia, despite being the language of a longstanding colonial power there. A \"union\" named for this language includes its country of origin as well as Suriname and Belgium, where the Flemish population speaks this tongue. For the point, name this language spoken in The Hague and Amsterdam.", "answer": "<b><u>Dutch</u></b> language [or <b><u>Nederlands</u></b>]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This franchise began with the 1947 purchase of a disbanded team, the Detroit Gems. The team then moved to Minnesota, where its name made more sense, though it has since moved west. Notable head coaches of this NBA team include Bill Sharman, Pat Riley, and Phil Jackson. For the point, name this NBA franchise with a record 16 NBA Championship titles, and which has showcased such talents as Kareem Abdul-Jabbar, Shaquille O'Neal, and Kobe Bryant.", "answer": "Los Angeles <b><u>Lakers</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>L</u></b>os <b><u>A</u></b>ngeles]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "One member of this political party was assassinated by the Polish glassmaker Janusz Walus and Clive Derby-Lewis. The militant wing of this political party was commanded by Oliver Tambo and was responsible for the Church Street Bombing. Leaders of that branch of this group, dubbed the \u201cSpear of the Nation\u201d, were indicted in the Rivonia Trial and sent to prison on Robben Island. For the point, name this political party whose leaders include Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "<b><u>African National Congress</u></b> [or <b><u>ANC</u></b>; accept <b><u>Spear of the Nation</u></b> before mention]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this year, Leonard Bernstein conducted a performance of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony where the word \u201cjoy\u201d was changed to \u201cfreedom.\u201d Erich Honecker resigned from his highest position in this year, the same year Nicolae Ceau\u015fescu (<b>choe-CHESS-koo</b>) and his wife were deposed and executed. V\u00e1clav Havel became his country's president after the Czech Velvet Revolution in this year. For the point, name this year that saw the fall of communism across Eastern Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>1989</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Members of the Blue Lights and Essex Junto were accused of collaborating with this foreign power. The Democratic-Republican Party coalesced following an unpopular treaty with this country negotiated by John Jay. This country negotiated with the U.S. in the Webster-Ashburton and Rush-Bagot Treaties. For the point, name this country whose king was the target of a list of grievances enumerated by Thomas Jefferson in the Declaration of Independence.", "answer": "<b><u>England</u></b> [or Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; or <b><u>U</u></b>nited <b><u>K</u></b>ingdom]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The leader of this organization became chair of the Labor Advisory Board during World War I in exchange for his support of the war effort and opposition to wartime strikes. This organization grew out of the Cigar Makers International and opposed Chinese immigration as competition for its members. For the point, name this labor union long led by Samuel Gompers,  which  has  since  merged  with  the  Congress  of  Industrial  Organizations.", "answer": "<b><u>American Federation of Labor</u></b> [<b><u>AFL</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The passage of the Constitution of May 3rd in this country prompted a 1791 invasion by Russia. This country\u2019s independence was sought in the failed November Uprising of 1830-1831, which was crushed by Nicholas I. This country was partitioned three times in the 18th century. After World War I, this country was restored to independence under Marshall Pilsudski. For the point, name this country which formed a Commonwealth with its neighbor Lithuania in 1569.", "answer": "<b><u>Poland</u></b> [accept <b><u>Poland Lithuana</u></b> or the <b><u>Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth</u></b> until \u201cPilsudski\u201d is read]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's administration employed a team of \"plumbers\" which worked closely with CREEP, and included G. Gordon Liddy. This man was advised to burn incriminating evidence by his advisor Pat Buchanan, and he could not explain the \"gap\" created by Rosemary Woods on his office taping system. For the point, name this President who resigned as a result of the break-in at Democratic Party campaign headquarters in the Watergate scandal.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Nixon</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During a less active theater of this war, Stephen Kearney commanded a mule dragoon corps and the Mormon Legion as part of his Army of the West. The pretext for this war was challenged in the Spot Resolutions, advanced by then-Congressman Abraham Lincoln. This war was ended a treaty negotiated by Nicholas Trist at Guadalupe Hidalgo which set the Rio Grande as the boundary. For the point, identify this 1846 war which the U.S. fought to its south.", "answer": "<b><u>Mexican</u></b>-American War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1981 this country's king urged citizens to reject the demands of soldiers holding its Parliament hostage. The Abraham Lincoln Brigade was a group of Americans who came here to fight in its civil war, which George Orwell described in <em>Homage to Catalonia</em>. During that war between Nationalists and Republicans, the Condor Legion destroyed the city of Guernica. For the point, name this country ruled for over thirty years by Francisco Franco.", "answer": "<b><u>Spain</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2005, a national campaign failed to prevent this action from being performed on \"Tookie\" Williams. This action was the subject of the <em>Atkins v. Virginia</em> and <em>Gregg v. Georgia</em> Supreme Court cases, which followed a mid-1970s moratorium on this practice after its pre-1972 usage was ruled \"cruel and unusual\" in <em>Furman v. Georgia</em>. For the point, name this act which has recently been abolished in New Jersey and Illinois, and may occur via lethal injection.", "answer": "<b><u>death penalty</u></b> (accept <b><u>capital punishment</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The destruction of this building is depicted on the Arch of Titus, and its spoils were sold off to fund the construction of the Coliseum. This structure received twelve loaves of \"showbread\" every day and contained an area entered only once per year known as the Holy of Holies. The only remaining portion of this building is the Western Wall, located near Al-Aqsa Mosque. For the point, name this second of two centers of ancient Jewish worship.", "answer": "Second Jewish <b><u>Temple</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "In 1989, this company established the Seeds of Change farm to create a line of organic foods. This company controls brands such as Orbit through its Wrigley subsidiary. This notoriously secretive company first allowed a reporter to watch its factory apply letters to candy in 1993. For the point, name this American candy company that manufactures Snickers and M&Ms, and shares its name with the planet where the Spirit and Opportunity rovers roamed.", "answer": "<b><u>Mars</u></b>, Inc.  <b>Extra (ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION!) </b> A community of these people at Kaifeng was known to Chinese neighbors for refusing to eat the sciatic nerve. The Khazar nobility of Central Asia converted into this religious group, which first arrived in the Americas in 1654 at Recife, Brazil. Members of this group were pejoratively called <em>falasha</em>s in Ethiopia. Early on, this religious group opposed the worship of Baal, the dominant tradition in Canaan. For the point, name this religious group from Israel.  ANSWER: <b><u>Jew</u></b>s [or <b><u>Jewish</u></b> people]", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}